well I'd like to introduce you to our
keynote speaker this morning Katie Bell
come on up katie is not like not yet
katie is a former software developer for
google of many years look like a veteran
run there and left there recently to
join a sydney-based startup named grok
learning working with high schools
building a platform for programming in
education something like that I think I
tangled up a few half sentences there
but I will hand directly over to her so
that I won't keep mincing my words round
of applause for Katie Bell please okay
is Mike on good all right yes I'm Katie
I worked for a company called grok
learning and to kind of give you an
explanation of what we do a groc
learning i'm going to take you through
thinking like a non programmer
approaching programming in Python for
the very first time and the way our
platform works is we have essentially an
online system it teaches you everything
you need to know about to pipe them in
order to do a series of challenge
questions those challenge questions
start off extraordinarily easy with
hello world and similar kinds of
variations before we move on to the
first kind of scary complicated question
where you're supposed to write a name
that right in it write a program that
asks the user what is your name and the
user then types in something and it
should say hello to the user with
whatever name they use a typed in who
thinks they could write this program
okay good stuff um ok so we're going to
go through the sort of series of thought
processes that are one of our students
Hamish started with so this is the first
attempt so the system works as you write
in your attempt at this program and then
you can hit you can run it yourself you
can see that it works the way you expect
it to work and then you can hit a mark
button that runs it through a series of
tests to give you feedback and help you
point help point you in the right to
for eventually getting the question
correct so hey measure in this case
copied exactly one of the examples from
the notes that had been reading through
which is good the student actually read
the notes um it's a good start but that
doesn't really answer the question your
program doesn't really work it says
hello and 10 and it's meant to say what
is your name so next attempt getting
much closer it's even like reading in
the input into a variable printing it
out that's pretty good but it's still
not exactly right and we emphasize this
right from the beginning in our course
that you must be very precise and we'll
get to that in a sec okay this time
we've got the space after the question
mark that's a good step um all right now
it's even sort of yeah not not quite
getting what's what's going on here but
you know it's printing out some extra
stuff yeah a report I wish is getting a
little bit confused and we're learning
from this Hamish is learning firstly
that computers are stupid the computers
not gonna understand what it means when
he says I'm hema Sh um when that
computers require precision is learning
to put spaces in the right places
learning that the output needs to be
exact okay so we go through um we have
another couple more attempts I up is
getting close it's just just got the
space wrong there okay oh and now it
fails the second test case um so it
works perfectly well as long as you type
in that your name is Brock and it
doesn't work at all if you type in
anything else and so all right so the
program is meant to print further now
okay
oh but now it's meant to print rock ah
this goes on for some time we miss Feld
further back to Brock again and then
eventually we get there um this is kind
of demonstrating how someone who has
never understood how a computer works
how programming works approaching it for
the first time is sort of learning
firstly the computers are stupid that
there but they also have to respond to
different kinds of input when I type in
something different the program has a
series of rules which it then responds
to and that's kind of the fundamental
piece of how programming works here's
another questions or getting rid of the
the sort of user interface around that
this is the question this is the answer
that we expect okay it's moving on this
is sort of after week one you've gotten
through multiple things you've learned
if statements you've learned while loops
you won learned for loops we're starting
to put them all together this is sort of
five weeks later in our course so this
is a much more complicated example we're
reading in one line of input at a time
appending it to a list reversing the
list and then printing it out in reverse
order this is my favorite attempt for
one of these questions it starts out
fine go to a while loop it's adding it
in for some reason it's also counting
how many things that's adding to the
while loop why is that because this is
how we're printing it out um so as part
of learning to program computer students
are also going to learn that they should
be avoiding unnecessary repetition
because eventually this doesn't work
this is what computers are good at the
good at repeating things over and over
again so that you don't have to I tried
to find an example of a student getting
mixed up about different data types
because this is one of the things that
really really killed students when
they're starting out with Python and
this was the best one I came up with
she's kind of got that there's something
wrong with trying to like add and
subtract strings but hasn't quite worked
out that they're already strings and
that string of firing them is not
actually going to help
but yeah this is a question one of the
students asked on the forum so is out of
learning that the data has the structure
to it in computing like a string is
fundamentally a different thing to an
integer and so on and as we learn lists
there are more complicated structures
and stuff so why are we teaching coding
who has heard this before coding is the
new literacy yeah some of you it's also
a complete crap um kind of I I get
really annoyed when people share this
kind of coating is a new literacy
everyone is going to need to be able to
code or you won't be able to get a job
um that sounds like a really terrible
plan to me um I don't want to have every
person in the world coding that's going
to end up with a lot of crappy and
redundant code and but what do we when
we're talking about how everyone should
learn to code why is it that we actually
want everyone to learn to code we
definitely don't want everyone to be
programmers we need a lot of people to
do other things as well and again we
don't want everyone writing copy code we
should be able to write the code once
and then it should be used multiple
times we shouldn't have everyone running
code so I propose that we change this
instead of talking about coding is the
new literacy should make hurting is the
new biology and before you like what the
hell let me explain that a little bit so
when you study biology at school firstly
you start studying it in primary school
you start with really simple things you
grow little broad beans or heads of
grass and stuff and you see that plants
need water and plants need sunlight and
as you get older you start to understand
that a lot more you learn about
photosynthesis you learn ah this is why
if we don't give any it plant any
sunlight it's going to die we don't give
it water adults are not going to survive
very long it makes sense of the world
around you and then you can reason about
it you have part of being an intelligent
human being in society's understanding
how photosynthesis works how we get food
every day how we don't die in the same
way
understanding how a computer works is
fundamental to being able to use them
well to be able to being able to reason
about them in society to be able to make
intelligent decisions as a voter when
technical issues come up and things so
going back to what our students were
learning as they were starting to
program their learning that there are
limitations to what computers can do
they can only do follow a series of
rules based on the inputs that they're
given if you could imagine how much
easier tech support would be if every
single user understood this if you can
they understand that the purpose of
computers is to avoid work for humans if
you understand what a computer is
capable of doing you're able to sit back
and write wait a minute why am i doing a
job that could be replaced by a computer
you don't need to be a professional
coder to have enough understanding to be
able to see that so every sir I leave
every student should learn to procured
at school during school and this helps
not only like attract more programmers
to the field because more people will
become interested in programming this
also helps fields which are very likely
to need coders like finance and science
and engineering where if you study
physics these days you study physics at
school we study physics at University
and you start doing research and
discover that you need to be able to
code in order to do that research and
then you have a crash course in coding
and a lot of physicists with very
terrible code I'm learning that earlier
would then help those fields that do
actually require coding it also helps
every other field because people will be
able to see how computers fit in how
compare our programming fits in what
kind of tools they can use what is
available to them it also helps
inclusivity you end up the current
system where students will only learn to
code if for some reason they are
expecting that they will find it
interesting and they choose to then
learn about it if you start off with
every single child learning about it
that gives every single child the
opportunity to find out if it's
something that they're interested in so
this helps women this helps minority is
generally a good thing so let's give
this a little bit more structure we're
going to dive in to how this actually
looks at a school level when you're
teaching coding am and as two examples
I'm going to look at the UK curriculum
and the new Australian Curriculum that's
coming out in the next couple of years
my understanding is that in New Zealand
at the moment the only curriculum for
coding is a an optional sort of high
later end of high school kind of thing
there's nothing for earlier on so this
is a fairly high level summary of the UK
code in curriculum and this came out in
the last couple of years and they've
started teaching it already a lot of
teachers are freaking out because they
don't know how to teach programming cuz
they don't know how to program
themselves but they're working on it so
notice that this starts really really
young at the top Key Stage one five and
six-year-olds starting to think about
algorithms and computational thinking so
this doesn't mean that we're getting
five year olds to start coding and
Python because they can sort of barely
read yet but we are starting to get five
and six-year-olds to think about things
in a computational thinking kind of way
how do I explain in a structured way how
to make toast in the morning what are
the decisions I make you can start to
think about branching decisions when he
thinks if it is raining then I should
take an umbrella otherwise I should
bring a hat we can start discussing
those things and developing those
algorithms in series of steps and
instructions and you'll also start to
talk about using technology and kind of
what it means when you're creating data
so creating storing retrieving digital
data could be very simple like taking a
photo and saving it to a hard drive
somewhere and then sending it to someone
else when you get to the sort of vs 7 to
11 year olds age group that's when they
start actually writing programs and in
the UK this is usually done with
something like scratch okay visual
programming language where they're
starting to write
programs would they actually have to
think okay I want the program to do this
they come up with a series of
instructions and steps you introduce
variables introduce branching they are
starting to learn that there's also
things in there about how networks and
the internet work how computers fit into
the daily lives there's also stuff
throughout the curriculum on using the
internet safely and using the impacts of
technology on society and sort of fuzzy
things like that as well um the key part
getting into the older kids which is
sort of 11 to 14 they have to learn two
different programming languages and at
least one of them has to be a text based
programming language and in the UK this
is almost always Python it is incredibly
common to be teaching Python in schools
in the UK at the moment there's also
particular things in the curriculum
about learning boolean logic and an or
operators how hardware and software how
computers work that they have a series
of instructions that they are executing
one by one and that data is represented
in binary moving on to the Australian
Curriculum this is the structure um
there is a much like again these are
very very like condensed versions of the
curriculum there's a lot of text in
there the Australian Curriculum is
divided into separate sort of course
streams these are only two of them there
is a couple more but starting in after
two which in the New Zealand system
would be 12 grade 1 2 3 again starting
describing algorithm starting to
identify the digital systems that you're
using every day starting to the really
basic things that you can do in a
classroom with a teacher and just paper
and white boards and stuff not even
touching a computer at this point the
the Australian Curriculum has a little
bit more detail in it than the UK
curriculum and it goes into more detail
specifically about how data is stored
and represented in numbers and in binary
and how getting onto the later ones our
text and images and sound data is
represented in binary but the
progression for programming is very
similar to the UK system where you start
out again
very young kids describing algorithms
then for the sort of primary school aged
kids you're using a visual programming
language starting off with input and
doing if statements and then getting to
more complicated things like loops but
again in year 7 and 8 which in the New
Zealand system would be your 89 you
learn a general-purpose programming
language and again the curriculum is
very language neutral um but you can see
how I think could fit in there so
talking about Python are you know some
of our students all right um why would
we teach Python in schools as opposed to
any other language and I really enjoy
teaching python python is definitely a
good language for teaching and it's
essentially good for the same reasons
that you guys all like python is because
it is very clean and simple especially
when you get started if you imagine this
program in java when you have glasses
and stuff there's a hell of a lot of
stuff that you have to explain away or
ignore as you're getting started and
you're in your first programs the other
thing i particularly like about python
is demonstrated by this example so i can
anyone see the problem with this i mean
the first problem is that it's in python
to never ever teach python sure and this
is probably my favorite reason why you
can see the bug with this yes okay you
will hit this before um yes for is
bigger than a thousand whoa album yep
for anyone that hasn't noticed the num
variable here is a string and in Python
too you can compare a string to a number
and it just kind of works except it only
works if it happens to the number
happens to be you greater than the
number that you wanted it to be greater
than in Python 30 so much better um I
cannot like describe to you how many
times I have seen students bashing their
heads against the wall for like why does
my if statement work only if the number
is less than the other number um this is
much better and this is what i like
about python particularly python 3 never
ever teach presenter
is because it had a lot of thought put
into it to make it clean and consistent
and nice arm if you've tried teaching
JavaScript and there's lots of random
little gotchas in there i think is much
nicer this makes it a particularly good
teaching language again for the same
reason that you guys curd in Python and
so as mentioned before this is really
where it fits in nicely in the UK
curriculum and again this is where it
fits in nicely with the Australian
Curriculum as well New Zealand is
usually a little bit ahead of Australia
and everything um but I you guys need a
code in curriculum ok this is the
problem with Python we're teaching
Python what is this idle here is years
the idol ide at some point in time ok
who actually uses it for anything useful
no nobody because did anyone here work
on idle at all ok good i can like and
safely i can safely just idle is really
annoying and it not only looks like crap
it's also it also it looks even works on
a mac um it's kind of painful to use in
the interpreter you can't even use the
up arrow to get back to your previous
commands but if you go into schools and
you see them teaching python this is
almost always what they're using and
it's kind of terrible at groc learning
we decided to put everything online so
we built our own we think else is better
and nicer but it does have the
disadvantage that it is online you can't
necessarily do pygame apps with it for
example because all of the Python is
running on our servers and you can't
really get a UI um so if you're doing
stuff locally idol is the kind of choice
and that's not particularly great but
there are a lot of really really cool
things that people are using Python for
and teaching with Python so I want to go
through a couple of those because
they're they're really cool examples of
what you can do so the raspberry pi
foundation has a lot of activities that
use Python are with the Raspberry Pi
this one is one of the examples where
you hook up a little tiny camera and a
button and Cody
only in Python you can write the code
that if you hit the button then it will
take a photo and it will store it and
you can use this to make little stop
motion videos and kids seem to love this
essentially you can do electronics
programming with Python which is pretty
awesome and so that's a really good way
to get kids doing something hands on
something that's interactive you there
is a Python API for Minecraft which lets
you place blocks and softness is also
really cool and engaging for kids this
is usually designed to run on the
Raspberry Pi but this can also run on
the regular Minecraft version as well
one of the things that we launched
recently at groc learning is using
turtle graphics or logo depending on
what generation you come from what you
call it and this is one for very very
beginning programming stuff where you
can actually sort of see the result SI
moving the total and it's turning left
and right and you can draw pretty
pictures and stuff with it which is cool
as well and there's always pie game
which always seems to end up looking
something like this but it is very
exciting for kids to have like stuff to
draw on the screen and stuff the
downside of Pi game is that there is a
lot that you have to cover to even get
started and doing anything is kind of a
little bit painful like yes okay I need
to work out the coordinates and all this
image on the screen and this exact
wouldn't it it could be a bit nicer but
it is very very cool and engaging so
this is um and explanation that I give
to people a lot when they're talking
about our but we should do this to get
kids excited turns out different kids
get excited about different things and
so when teaching programming there these
are the three different kind of major
areas that I see kids get excited about
when they're learning to code some kids
get excited purely about the algorithmic
problem solving steps where they don't
really care what the code is actually
doing as long as they're like enjoying
the thought process of I have to do this
thing and now how do i formulate that
incurred to make it through the thing
that I want some kids get excited
learning how computers actually work
learning what is going on and sort of
building things at the very low level
tens of gravitating more to the
electronics and robotics kind of stuff
and then there's kind of the the
building cool stuff I kids who they
don't kind of care like what the process
is to get there but they want something
that they can really show off at the end
and this is kind of the the difficult
part for Python so apart from all of the
cool stuff that I showed you that you
can teach with Python the problem with
all of those is that they are very much
toys they are not real world python
applications and this works really
really well for the younger primary
school-aged kids but when they're
getting older we need something to then
bring that back together and sure hey
you just learned a real-world skill that
can build the kinds of software that you
use yourself every day so they want to
learn like hey this is a kill that I
could use to build something that will
actually genuinely be useful in my life
that people might actually want to use I
could be a product or something so my
question to you is where is your Python
running sorry if you guys are all Python
developers put your hand up if your code
is running in some way that is useful to
a person other than you cool so your
code is running somewhere it's in it's
in production it's its launch to the
user okay so for your hand up again if
your code is not running on your own
servers somewhere okay is it actually
running on a desktop device or a mobile
device a couple of you that's actually
more than I expected um that is
interesting um essentially my experience
most of what Python developers do is run
on Linux servers somewhere in the cloud
somewhere as some kind of web server
like this um and it's very hard to find
ways to use Python to develop the kinds
of apps and tools that the kids actually
know as the ones that they're using so
they the kids know I have this app that
I install on my foreign or there's a
software that I can run on my computer
as a game or something like that these
are the sort of tangible software pieces
that they're familiar
and if they could build those they could
really see the value of what they're
doing the way we've gotten around this
in the past is by getting kids to use
Python to build a web server to build a
website which is interactive and they
and they can take things into forms and
then it stores but the downside of this
is that is actually a really huge
project to get anything working if you
want a kid to be able to write a Python
web server they need to understand HTML
I need to understand CSS if it wants to
look not like crap they need to
understand how HTTP works and you need
some kind of database for storing stuff
in so usually that would be some kind of
SQL database and so you're suddenly
teaching for different kinds of writing
like you know I HTML CSS Python and SQL
in order just to get something working
that looks like a website that was made
10 years ago now because there's no
JavaScript if you want JavaScript you
have to learn yet another language um so
we do this and I have seen this work in
schools where you have a particularly
motivated teacher that actually
understands all of these different
things themselves and can guide the
students through that um but this is
mostly the time completely infeasible
for schools so we are so this is kind of
my my challenge to you guys um is we
have kids and we have teachers coming to
us and saying I want to build an app can
I do that with Python it's like well it
kind of made me you could um but we want
kids that I want to build a game and
then I just want to be able to send that
to my friends and then they can run it
and play it and I was like well I guess
you could package it up and um and I'll
let you guess which one of these comes
from a teacher when we're teaching
Python um the teachers are like yes
they're getting into it and they're
really excited but like we need
something that
is visually engaging that then they can
they can build interactive things and
stuff and this is this is generally a
bit hard in Python so this is my
challenge to you firstly replace idle
and make a better idea because that
would be awesome some kind of simple and
powerful graphical interface toolkit
where I can just kind of draw a button
and then write very very simple code so
i can click that button then something
happens that would be awesome to make
python work on mobile there are some
projects already underway for this which
look really cool so I'm excited about
that but at the moment I would not
recommend writing yeah um and one thing
that I thought would be particularly
cool coming from New Zealand is that I
understand that python is the scripting
language for pretty much all 3d
animation stuff but I've never seen
anyone make this work in a classroom
where you have a bunch of kids like that
would be a very cool very interactive
real-world application of Python but I
have not seen anyone do this so if
anyone's working in the 3d animation
industry talk to me afterwards that
would be very cool and the teachers will
thank you we have we had like in you
know i grok learning we have contact
with a lot of different teachers and
then we get the feedback yes we are
loving learning python the kids are
getting really into it what can we do
next um so any kind of stuff from that
would begin apart from that we really
need advocates advocates for teaching
coding in schools and not only that even
if we do get coding taught in schools in
order to get a generation of kids that
actually understand computers coming
through the teachers are going to need a
lot of help so anything that you guys
can do to help train teachers to learn
to program to program and to teach
programming is going to be really
valuable I tend to try and shy away from
coding clubs where the kids are choosing
to go and be there because you're
usually only getting the kids that are
already interested in learning to code
and can maybe do it in their spare time
or their parents are computer scientists
or something but running a workshop in
the school where you're taking a whole
class
is much more valuable because then
there's a whole ton of kids that never
would have understood programming at all
before that who are then getting
exposure to it or become a teacher so
coders who then become teachers also
very cool because then you'll actually
have coding skills in the classroom as
well ah so that's cool that's me doc I
think I might have talked a little bit
too fast but there's lots of time
questions cool let's open up for
questions I'll run right and bring the
mic to you so someone raised their hands
Brenda hi I love what you're doing and I
really want to do this stuff too but how
do you fund all this here I have a day
job I don't have a time how do you do
this that is a good question um so the
sort of group that this started with I
was the national computer science school
so this is the National in the in
Australia um run by Sydney University
from the one of the academics a couple
of the academics there and they've been
running a summer camp teaching Python
well not originally teaching by thing
because it started 20 years ago but for
the last 16 years teaching Python at
this summer camp unfortunately the
summer camp has the same problem as
every other coding club you are only
reaching the couple of students that
elected to come there and so the Sir
James Cowan one of the academics in the
university started an online Python
programming competition which also
teaches Python in order to reach a lot
more kids and that was starting to reach
the order of 10,000 kids every year
wanted to expand this more but wasn't
getting enough backing from the
University and so this is why grok
learning started as a separate company
so grok learning is a tiny for-profit
company where we charge twenty dollars
per student to learn Python online and
that is where the money comes from the
sort of small amounts of it yes
um ah thank you for your presentation my
question is up I went to my children's
school and told the principal that i
would like to run a linux a workshop at
some stage and the principal told me
that she has to go to some Department of
Education get the permission and this
all red tape blocked my proposal at that
time and she never came back to me so my
question to you is that for the local
you may have run already some workshops
in the school how do you approach and
can you be with them put some more light
on to it please how do you a virgin um
so I'm not entirely sure what the
problems were in that case but there are
certain processes that you need to go
through to have a background check and
stuff done to be okay um apart on that
oh you really would need is a permission
of the school i'm not sure what else the
school would need for that okay um so
sorry so I work in the school's this
admin but you know the school that I'm
working is that I used to study and so
and basically can say that my teacher
kind of pushed me into programming in
this is one I'm stead of handling this
you know then you guys but I found this
a lot of like you know i'm bout teach it
does a lot of you know a lot of effort
into teaching as programming and after
I've been in uni I found that a lot of
kids don't even learn half what we
learned in our yes in our program and
it's very hard to encourage teachers to
learn new stuff such as I'm trying to
encourage the our teacher to learn get
because I'm sick of looking six versions
of the same pitch because it's just
horrible so how do you encourage
teachers to to learn program how to
encourage them to stop learning how to
do a freaking PowerPoint presentations
and look at something interesting those
kids are suffering from the fact that
teachers don't want to do anything about
that fact oh yes so that is unfortunate
right there's there's not a lot that you
can do to make it make someone learn
something new when do something in a
different way to what they were doing it
before and that goes for every year
every kind of in
not just teachers like getting out of
the pattern of that what you were in
before this is a big problem because
we're coding in particular because you
get some kids that have been coding
since they were eight years old and
they've like already they get to
university and they're like why are we
learning java or you know java and you
get other kids that have no idea what
programming is because they've never
seen it before and you have this huge
disparity yes this is exactly the kind
of problem that having a set curriculum
across all schools is designed to solve
yours essentially define this is the
minimum standard that we expect students
to achieve at school and this is the
purpose of curriculum this is I don't
see any way to actually get coding
taught in schools without it being part
of the mandated curriculum you can
encourage and you can sort of prod as
much as you want and say don't worry you
don't have to teach it I can come to
your school and then teach a Dora
something like that but ultimately
you're never going to get this in every
school everywhere unless it is enforced
yeah yes yeah my question to you is a
you said that we need a better idea but
what is the use case often ide what but
when I learn Python I found it much more
useful to just use a good edit text
editor and Python maybe ipython as a
shell to toy around with but I never
needed something more than a decent text
editor how so that is that is an
interesting point as in I've seen this
occasionally where a student becomes a
lot more engaged when they use the
command line then when they using
somekind of prepackaged ID but
ultimately it's it's less scary when
you're first starting out if you have
sort of air all the information that you
need in one place kids are typically bad
at typing they're bad at switching
between different windows and managing
all the kind of muscle memory tabbing
between different windows and stuff
isn't something that you have in primary
school and so even idle where you have
two different windows where you have a
different window for your text editor in
a different window for your interpreter
gets really confusing for kids and I've
seen this
and having some kind of platform where
you have here's my card and here is the
code running and I can see both at the
same time as useful and it will show you
highlight a particular line when you've
got a syntax error or something like
that so I think there is a lot of value
in having an ID in making those initial
steps to get into programming much
easier there is only one thing that you
have to download install you don't also
have to learn how to use a command line
in order to be able to program in I just
following up on your point about how in
Python 2 with the input for the number
and the fact that if you don't convert
it to a number then you get a program
that runs but just does completely the
wrong thing yeah sorry versus Python 3
which runs but then crashes with a
useful error message yeah my question is
why not use a language that just doesn't
give you a program at all and just gives
you a useful type error instead and note
that I am very much not implying that
you use Java for that what do you mean
that gives you a useful type error as an
how is that different to work what
Python does well yeah I mean yeah I mean
Haskell or or or a language like that
and I mean it's more I'm well yeah I
resent the fact that you implied that we
all like Python here I consider it the
best I consider it the best of a bad
bunch and I'm firmly in the canister
programming languages but I hate fight
and slightly less than a lot of the
other ones yes yeah so um you know I
don't think dynamically typed languages
are the right languages for people to be
using and therefore I don't think that
they're the right languages I know I
will admit this as well um Python would
be a hell of a lot easier to teach if we
declared the types when we declared the
variables if there if it was statically
typed that way because explaining that
this variable is an end and this
variable is a string and that you
add them together is much easier when
each variable has int or strain written
next to it now you can but the kids
aren't going to do that um so yes I
agree that having the sort of type
definitions would make it easier to
teach I have not found a language that
is better to teach them Python door okay
I was just thinking about your idea of
an IDE better than I'd all but you know
a lot of ideas for Python I think would
probably be way overpowered for the club
audience you're discussing almost always
the one that comes up is Piton the
Community Edition because it's free
right um pai tom is like eclipse for
Python um it is very cool if you're I
guess has lots of cool features and
stuff but it is incredibly like just way
too many buttons way too many controls
it is very confusing for kids aspect
would i look would like an event okay um
it has to have syntax highlighting it
has to tell you what error like which
line the errors are on you have to be
able to run it in the same window so
that you can see here is my code and
here is my code running um at a minimum
that would be that would be it and it
has to be not painful to use let's go
with that but very clean very simple um
i highly recommend if you've ever seen
gosh or to last name Carrie Ann from the
raspberry pi foundation I gave a really
great keynote at euro python last year
and also at PyCon Australia this year oh
no both of them is with this year um and
what a large part of what she talked
about was hear all of the different
things that people use of Python IVs and
why they all suck um this is what I want
in an IDE so talk to her she has a lot
of opinions on this and they are good
opinions yes okay okay yes thanks very
much for you talk by the way the the
Twittersphere education people are
already I'm frothing at the mouth for
the video of this talk because they okay
so they're already looking at groc
learning calm and all that sort of thing
so that's good I was just wondering with
regard to the teaching of teachers in
this very room a few years ago I was
first introduced to something called
software carpentry I don't know if
anybody hears come across that but it's
a Canadian run effort but it's an
international and international program
designed to teach primarily scientists
how to make better use of computing so
that they can amplify their research
capabilities and also do things properly
rather than as you pointed out writing a
whole lot of code badly and they the
software carpentry trains people to
become bootcamp teachers so they get
people into a three day boot camp where
they learn the command line other on
Linux are on a Mac because Windows
doesn't do it and they have they learned
then immediately get and then they learn
ipython by popping notebooks which
actually I think to certain extent will
address some of the IDE questions that
you also ask potentially yeah okay
anyway I realize it's a bit more ground
yeah sledgehammer for a brass tack but
anyway yeah so it would be interesting
to see whether you guys could perhaps
join forces with software carpentry to
instruct teachers because the curriculum
materials are all in github they're all
open they're all creative commons
licensed and otherwise open source cool
that's a really good idea I think I have
met someone from software copy beautiful
um but yeah we hadn't discussed like
collaborating on that sir yes I have
another question about typing and
functional programming and that kind of
stuff I totally agree that item is
probably the best language to teach but
if we have plans to teach kids more than
one language do you know if there's been
some thought about what other language
and in my opinion it should be a highly
s antonius functional programming
language like the opposite of piety I
can see how that you know 10 15 years
from now wants everyone it once teaches
a comfortable teaching one paradigm of
programming that maybe we would it would
be cool to also teach a functional
language in schools as well and maybe
next time we update the curriculum in 20
years it will be
learning one language isn't enough we
should also learn a functional language
I don't think that is feasible at this
time but it is a very interesting idea
and if there was a teacher that was very
keen to be teaching that that would be
that would be completely supported by
the curriculum its language independent
I would like to go back to my favorite
diagram this one where the functional
paradigm as a sort of problem solving
and way of thinking will be fascinating
force the kids that love the problem
solving an algorithms side the it does
not necessarily help you so much with
building cool stuff that then you can
show off to your friends and so it'd be
a little bit hesitant about teaching or
only that but if it was in conjunction
with another language as well that would
be cool yeah so in terms of number of
languages required to deal with web apps
maybe pop a genius oh I have not seen
this before or this that sounds kind of
scary to be honest it is um okay just
putting it out there but I remember
vividly in high school when we were
doing physics they told us that atoms
were made up of this big ball of
something which was called Nicholas and
it had currents no no that there were
electrons which looked like currents or
possibly raisins inside and then the
next year they said forget everything we
told you last year was a lie they're
actually like the Sol system than their
their whizzing around and then I believe
if I kept going to university they were
safe forget everything you got told it
was all the conservation of mass and
then later on it's like well really
conservation of mass is conservation of
energy isn't so the question is well
it's not a quick now i'm going to say
stay down i'm sure that that applies to
teaching kids programming that you may
want to teach them functional but that's
kind of maybe the third year lie you
should start with the really simple lie
and say hey pythons gonna give you
everything you need no it's not like
you're going to need the function
actually we lied you're going to need a
sink in the future
yeah yeah as long as kids are learning
the sort of fundamental I have this
problem and I break it down into a
series of steps that then the computer
can understand oh that is a huge step
and that will get them a big advantage
later on as I go to university and then
study actual programming yes hey yeah
schools often interested in examining
what the students have done and I found
when I went to school that the
examination er wasn't really that great
but i really enjoy things like a google
code jam where you actually get problems
that are interesting and you have to
solve them in a certain time so things
like that might be good to look into if
you're running against the wall off how
do we examine this oh yeah that is that
is an interesting question a lot of
exams a stool at school will be done on
paper so if a school was learning a
particular programming language they are
likely to be doing exams in that
programming language as for the the sort
of cross school exams if there are any
in the future the way this is done at
the moment in a language-independent way
is by doing pseudocode algorithms in the
exam but yes I agree would absolutely
absolutely be much better to have sort
of online timed exams where you write
code and you can actually run the code
before submitting it
okay so there's no call record involved
in the exam yeah okay hi there just I
like that diagram you have the air too
because it is actually doing things one
of the things I think the people in this
room because we've both in programmers
or programmers of any description is
we've already actually pulled ourselves
into one particular spot in the complete
set of types of ways of thinking about
problems and things and so do you go
talking to your two teachers to staff to
treachery try and find you know
different angles and ways of doing it
how are you getting good feedback Aug
communicating well with the teaching
sort of industry generally yes so
through running out online courses we
have essentially a set of forums where
the kids can ask questions and so we get
very very immediate feedback on what the
kids are understanding and what they're
not understanding based on the questions
that we're getting in the forms and you
we answer them we help them through and
we can find better ways of explaining
things to different kids as we go
through we also get a lot of feedback
from teachers on what they like and what
they don't like we've had teachers been
who've been using our system for five or
six years now and we get and they're if
there's anything that they don't like
simply find out very quickly um and we
get a lot of feedback on them from them
how to improve it sir yeah there's a lot
of a lot of communication there let's
hope this is on it works a very basic
question of how many students are using
your system roughly at the moment and
not so basic what kind of demographics
other it's probably best explained oh I
don't have internet on it moment
okay um so our big thing of the year is
this competition that we run which is
just in its final week now and that gets
about 10,000 students and the age groups
range quite significantly so the what I
wanted to show you is that we have four
different levels of difficulty um and if
I turn the internet on this is it then
so we have what we call newbies
beginners intermediate and advanced and
newbies uh okay that's fine I'll just
use my roaming well that is not remain
it's a local sim um there we go okay so
we have a new breeze beginners
intermediate and advanced or four
different levels of difficulty newbies
is usually primary school kids but we
have kids up to like so you're sort of
grades four five and six um and the way
actually it's not a good example of a
question let's go back okay
it's also not a good example that's true
I see one of the later ones sure okay so
this is actually a set of blocks that
click together that then generate Python
um so this is what we start the
beginners on when they're in the sort of
primary school age and this scroll bar
isn't working very well okay um so you
have for example the first line is
assigning to a variable with some input
and that generates the Python directly
there so as you're you're changing the
blocks and you're sort of doing stuff
around that kind of thing um it is
editing the Python right in front of you
we find this is a good way to transition
kids into actually doing Python so we
don't start Python directly necessarily
with a sort of year five and six kids
but that is where we start the other
ones are just plain writing Python
beginners starts out with just Heller
world input and goes up to lists and
intermediate starts at the beginning of
all goes a bit faster advanced is quite
advanced and does some interesting
computer science there we do have a huge
range of abilities visually we have
different levels and so the wii range
all the way from grade 5 to grade 12 or
grade 6 to grade 13 in the new zealand
grade system yep hey oh yeah
um we do get schools across the board
but we do tend to two it does tend to
balance more to the higher end schools
the like wealthy schools and the the
more selective schools yeah yeah kind of
a follow up question about demographics
dizzam gras cloning have any ambitions
to cross the ditch or run the National
Computer Science advances this challenge
is open to new zealand students it's all
online so there's nothing really
stopping anyone in the world from
participating in it and we do get a
whole bunch of kids from new zealand and
we have quite a few schools from New
Zealand as well participating and do you
have quite a few people just doing the
courses not through the challenge fun
yes less so sorry the channel the the
competition with its very structured
time frame works well as a motivator
like here is here is the deadline you
have to start the course now here for
the finish the course now you get a lot
more people that way than just having a
course that's open all the time but
people say hey this is cool last out
later and then never do so we do have
courses that are available all the time
as well introduction programming and
HTML and CSS course and stuff but most
of what we get is the competitions yeah
we have time for one more question
just from the list of tests that I saw
you were doing on the input and from the
kind of mistakes you said people made it
seemed like a lot of that kind of thing
is just what would be picked up on by
people using auto-completion obviously
like people in this room would argue
that's a crutch I wonder like what's
your opinion on that like do you think
that's an important feature to have and
like have you had a chance to do any
testing on students for whether it helps
no I haven't done any testing on that
and that would be interesting to find
out that is one of the big differences
between the blocks and coding in Python
yourself because the blocks are all here
and you can look them up and find the
block that you need and then just put it
in rather than having to remember how to
type everything but the blocks obviously
get annoying to use and having we
haven't done any experiments with
autocomplete to see if that would help
because we don't have an order complete
system built into our site that would be
an interesting experiment to run and I
don't know what the outcome would be I
suspect that you would get a lot of kids
if you can rely on alter order complete
in the early problems then if they're
not fully understanding the concepts
later that could be a real problem um
but again it could also just avoid kids
getting stuck and throwing their hands
up in frustration and giving up sir cool
please join me one one more time and
thinking Katie Bell for her
you