we can extract from a data frame by
speaker we can extract by vowel and we
can combine those conditions and the
magic here is the ampersand operator
that's what we're going to use to
combine conditions so let's just do it
one by one again I start by loading D
plier using the library command and then
first I'm going to define a vector that
contains the vowels that I want to
extract let's say trap and kit and then
I define a vector that contains the
names of the speakers that I want to
extract this could be used to define a
group of four people for example if you
have a larger data set I only have Allen
Erma I'll use them both here because why
not okay and then I'm going to make a
new data frame that is a subset of my
master norm I'm going to call it new
data and I'm going to use the filter
command to filter out of master norm
filter out of master norm comma and now
the conditions the vowel needs to be
percent in percent the my vowels vector
so it needs to be a member of that
vector drop and KITT and now it combined
with the ampersand and the condition
speaker must be in the speaker's vector
which I just defined so and I want rows
that meet both of these conditions
either Al or Emma saying either a trap
or a KITT vowel now I just ran those
first three lines of code and now I'm
running the fourth line of code
separately and I'm gonna click on my new
data frame and it's gonna be shown in
the preview event window top left and
that's all I have is Emma and Al and
they're saying either KITT words
trap words
[Music]